<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY rfc1033 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1033.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc1034 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc1035 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2045 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2045.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2104 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2104.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2782 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2782.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4055 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4055.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4075 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4075.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4279 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4279.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5246 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5705 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5705.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5246 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6124 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6124.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6151 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6151.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6189 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6189.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6762 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6762.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6763 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6763.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc7296 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7296.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc7626 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7626.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc7844 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7844.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc7858 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7858.xml'>

<!ENTITY I-D.huitema-dnssd-privacy PUBLIC ''
   "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.huitema-dnssd-privacy.xml">

<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-intarea-hostname-practice PUBLIC ''
   "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-intarea-hostname-practice.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dprive-dnsodtls PUBLIC ''
   "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dprive-dnsodtls.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-tls-tls13 PUBLIC ''
   "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-tls-tls13.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dnssd-push PUBLIC ''
   "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dnssd-push">
<!ENTITY I-D.miers-tls-sas PUBLIC ''
   "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.miers-tls-sas">


<!ENTITY kw14a PUBLIC ''
   "references/reference.kw14a.xml">
<!ENTITY kw14b PUBLIC ''
   "references/reference.kw14b.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

<!-- Expand crefs and put them inline -->
<?rfc comments='yes' ?>
<?rfc inline='yes' ?>

<rfc category="std"
     docName="draft-kaiser-pairing-01.txt"
     ipr="trust200902">

<front>
    <title abbrev="Device Pairing">
      Device Pairing Using Short Authentication Strings
    </title>

   <author fullname="Christian Huitema" initials="C." surname="Huitema">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street> </street>
          <city>Clyde Hill</city>
          <code>98004</code>
          <region>WA</region>
          <country>U.S.A.</country>
        </postal>
        <email>huitema@huitema.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

   <author fullname="Daniel Kaiser" initials="D." surname="Kaiser">
     <organization>University of Konstanz</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street> </street>
          <city>Konstanz</city>
          <code>78457</code>
          <region></region>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <email>daniel.kaiser@uni-konstanz.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2016" />

    <abstract>
        <t>
          This document proposes a device pairing mechanism that establishes a relationship between two devices by
          agreeing on a secret and manually verifying the secret's authenticity using an SAS (short authentication string).
          Pairing has to be performed only once per pair of devices, as for a re-discovery at any later point in time,
          the exchanged secret can be used for mutual authentication.
        </t>
        <t>
          The proposed pairing method is suited for each application area where human operated devices need to establish a
          relation that allows configurationless and privacy preserving re-discovery at any later point in time.
          Since privacy preserving applications are the main suitors, we especially care about privacy.
        </t>
    </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section title="Introduction">
  <t>
  To engage in secure and privacy preserving communication, hosts need to differentiate
  between authorized peers, which must both know about the host's presence and be able to decrypt messages sent by the host,
  and other peers, which must not be able to decrypt the host's messages and ideally should  not be aware of the host's presence.
  The necessary relationship between host and peer can be established by a centralized service, e.g. a certificate  authority,
  by a web of trust, e.g. PGP, or -- without using global identities -- by device pairing.
  </t>
  
  <t>
    This document proposes a device pairing mechanism that provides human operated devices with pairwise authenticated secrets,
    allowing mutual automatic re-discovery at any later point in time along with mutual private authentication.
    We especially care about privacy and user-friendliness.
  </t>

  <t>
    The proposed pairing mechanism consists of three steps needed to establish a relationship between a host and a peer:
  </t>

  <t>
<list style="numbers">
<t>
   Discovery of the peer device. The host needs a means to discover network parameters necessary to establish a connection to the peer.
   During this discovery process, neither the host nor the peer must disclose its presence.
</t>
<t>
  Agreeing on pairing data. The devices have to agree on pairing data, which can be used by both parties at any later point in time to
  generate identifiers for re-discovery and to prove the authenticity of the pairing.
  The pairing data can e.g. be a shared secret agreed upon via a Diffie-Hellman key exchange.
</t>
<t>
  Authenticate pairing data. Since in most cases the messages necessary to agree upon pairing data are send over an insecure channel, 
  means that guarantee the authenticity of these messages are necessary;
  otherwise the pairing data is in turn not suited as a means for a later proof of authenticity.
  For the proposed pairing mechanism we use manual interaction involving an SAS 
  (short authentication string) to proof the authenticity of the pairing data.
</t>
</list>
</t>

<section title="Requirements">
<t>
  The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
  "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
  document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.
</t>
</section>
</section>


<section title="Problem Statement and Requirements" anchor="problem" >
<t>
The general pairing requirement is easy to state: establish a trust relation between two entities in a 
secure manner. But details matter, and in this section we explore the detailed requirements that guide
our design.
</t>

<section title="Secure Pairing Over Internet Connections" anchor="securityReq" >
<t>
Many pairing protocols have already been developed, in particular for the
pairing of devices over specific wireless networks. For example, the current Bluetooth 
specifications include a pairing protocol that has evolved over several
revisions towards better security and usability <xref target="BTLEPairing" />.
The Wi-Fi Alliance defined the Wi-Fi Protected Setup process to ease the setup of 
security-enabled Wi-Fi networks in home and small office environments 
<xref target="WPS" />. Other wireless standards have defined or are defining similar
protocols, tailored to specific technologies.
</t>
<t>
This specification defines a pairing protocol that is independent of the underlying 
technology. We simply make the hypothesis that the two parties engaged in the pairing
can discover each other and then establish connections over IP in order to
agree a shared secret.
</t>
<t>
[[TODO: Should we support certificates besides a shared secret?]]
</t>
</section>

<section title="Identity Assurance" anchor="verifyId">
<t>
The parties in the pairing must be able to identify each other. To put it simply, if Alice believes 
that she is establishing a pairing with Bob, she must somehow ensure that the pairing is actually
established with Bob, and not with some interloper like Eve or Nessie.
Providing this assurance requires designing both the protocol and the user interface (UI) with care.
</t>
<t>
Consider for example an attack in 
which Eve tricks Alice into engaging in a pairing process while pretending to be Bob. Alice must be able 
to discover that something is wrong, and refuse to establish the pairing.
The parties engaged in the pairing must at least be able to verify their identities, respectively.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Adequate User Interface" anchor="MITMUIReq" >
<t>
Because the pairing protocol is executed without prior knowledge, it is typically vulnerable to
"Man-in-the-middle" attacks. While Alice is trying to establish a pairing with Bob, Eve positions 
herself in the middle. Instead of getting a pairing between Alice and Bob, both Alice and Bob get
paired with Eve. This requires specific features in the protocol to
detect man-in-the-middle attacks, and if possible resist them. The reference <xref target="NR11" /> 
analyzes the various proposals to solve this problem, and in this document, we present 
a layman description of these issues in <xref target="MITMCryptoReq" />. The
various protocols proposed in the literature impose diverse constraints on the UI
interface, which we will review here.
</t>

<section title="Short PIN Proved Inadequate" >
<t>
The initial Bluetooth pairing protocol relied on a four digit PIN, displayed by one of the devices to be paired.
The user would read that PIN and provide it to the other device.
The PIN would then be used in a Password Authenticated Key Exchange.
Wi-Fi Protected Setup <xref target="WPS" /> offered a similar option.
There were various attacks against the actual protocol; some of the problems were caused by issues
in the protocol, but most were tied to the usage of short PINs.
</t>
<t>
In the reference implementation, the PIN is picked at random by the paired device before
the beginning of the exchange. But this requires that the paired device is capable of
generating and displaying a four digit number. It turns out that many devices cannot do
that. For example, an audio headset does not have any display capability. These limited
devices ended up using static PINs, with fixed values like "0000" or "0001".
</t>
<t>
Even when the paired device could display a random PIN, that PIN will have to be copied
by the user on the pairing device. It turns out that users do not like copying long
series of numbers, and the usability thus dictated that the PINs be short -- four digits
in practice. But there is only so much assurance as can be derived from a four digit key.
</t>
<t>
It is interesting to note that the latest revisions of the Bluetooth Pairing protocol 
<xref target="BTLEPairing" /> do not include the short PIN option anymore. The 
PIN entry methods have been superseded by the simple "just works" method for devices
without displays, and by a procedure based on an SAS (short authentication string) when
displays are available.
</t>

<t>
A further problem with these PIN based approaches is that -- in contrast to SASes --
the PIN is a secret instrumental in the security algorithm.
To guarantee security, this PIN had to be transmitted via a secure out of band channel.
</t>

</section>

<section title="Push Buttons Just Work, But Are Insecure" >
<t>
Some devices are unable to input or display any code. The industry more or less
converged on a "push button" solution. When the button is pushed, devices enter
a "pairing" mode, during which they will accept a pairing request from whatever 
other device connects to them.
</t>
<t>
The Bluetooth Pairing protocol <xref target="BTLEPairing" /> denotes that as 
the "just works" method. It does indeed work, and if the pairing succeeds
the devices will later be able to use the pairing keys to authenticate connections.
However, the procedure does not provide any protection against
MITM attacks during the pairing process. The only protection is that pushing the
button will only allow pairing for a limited time, thus limiting the
opportunities of attacks.
</t>
<t>
As we set up to define a pairing protocol with a broad set of applications,
we cannot limit ourselves to an insecure "push button" method. But we probably
need to allow for a mode of operation that works for input-limited
and display limited devices.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Short Range Communication" anchor="shortRange" >
<t>
There have been several attempts to define pairing protocols that use "secure
channels." Most of them are based on short range communication systems,
where the short range limits the feasibility for attackers to access the channels.
Example of such limited systems include for example:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols" >
<t>
QR codes, displayed on the screen of one device, and read by the camera of the other device.
</t>
<t>
Near Field Communication (NFC) systems, which provides wireless communication with a very short range.
</t>
<t>
Sound systems, in which one systems emits a sequence of sounds or ultrasounds that is picked by the microphone of the other system.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
A common problem with these solutions is that they require special capabilities that may not be present in every device. 
Another problem is that they are often one-way channels. Yet another problem is that the side channel is not
necessarily secret. QR codes could be read by third parties. Powerful radios antennas might be able to interfere with 
NFC. Sensitive microphones might pick the sounds. We will discuss the specific case of QR codes in <xref target="QRDiscuss" />.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Short Authentication Strings" >
<t>
The evolving pairing protocols seem to converge towards a "display and compare" method. 
This is in line with academic studies, such as <xref target="KFR09" /> or <xref target="USK11" />.
This points to a very simple scenario:
</t>
<t>
<list style="numbers">
<t>
Alice initiates pairing
</t>
<t>
Bob selects Alice's device from a list.
</t>
<t>
Alice and Bob compare displayed strings that represent a fingerprint of the key.
</t>
<t>
If the strings match, Alice and Bob accept the pairing.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Most existing pairing protocols display the fingerprint of the key as a 6 or 7 digit
numbers. Usability studies show that gives good results, with little risk that
users mistakenly accept two different numbers as matching. However, the authors of 
<xref target="USK11" /> found that people had more success comparing computer 
generated sentences than comparing numbers. This is in line with the argument in
<xref target="XKCD936" /> to use sequences of randomly chosen common words as passwords. 
On the other hand, standardizing strings is more complicated than standardizing numbers.
We would need to specify a list of common words, and the process to go from a binary 
fingerprint to a set of words. We would need to be concerned with internationalization 
issues, such as using different lists of words in German and in English. This could
require negotiation of word lists or languages inside the pairing protocols. 
</t>
<t>
In contrast, numbers are easy to specify, as in "take a 20 bit number and 
display it as an integer using decimal notation."
</t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="Resist Cryptographic Attacks" anchor="MITMCryptoReq" >
<t>
It is tempting to believe that once two peers are connected, they could create
a secret with a few simple steps, such as for example exchange two nonces, 
hash the concatenation of these nonces with the shared secret that is about to be established, display
a short authentication string composed of a short version of that hash 
on each device, and verify that the two values match. The sequence
of messages would be something like:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
    Alice                       Bob
    g^xA --&gt;
                           &lt;-- g^xB
    nA --&gt;
                              &lt;-- nB
    Computes              Computes
    s = g^xAxB            s = g^xAxB
    h = hash(s|nA|nB)     h = hash(s|nA|nB)
    Displays short        Displays short
    version of h          version of h
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
If the two short hashes match, Alice and Bob are supposedly assured that
they have computed the same secret, but there is a problem.
The exchange may not deter a smart attacker
in the middle. Let's redraw the same message flow, this time involving Eve:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
    Alice                Eve                Bob
    g^xA --&gt;
                         g^xA'--&gt;
                                        &lt;-- g^xB
                      &lt;--g^xB'
    nA --&gt;
                         nA --&gt; 
                                          &lt;-- nB
                       Picks nB'
                       smartly
                      &lt;--nB'
    Computes                             Computes
    s' = g^xAxB'                           s" = g^xA'xB
    h' = hash(s|nA|nB')                    h" = hash(s"|nA|nB)
    Displays short                       Displays short
    version of h'                        version of h"
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
Let's now assume that to pick the nonce nB' smartly, Eve runs the following
algorithm:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
    s' = g^xAxB'
    s" = g^xA'xB
    repeat
       pick a new version of nB'
       h' = hash(s|nA|nB')
       h" = hash(s"|nA|nB)
    until the short version of h' 
    matches the short version of h"
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
Of course, running this algorithm will require in theory as many iterations as
the possible values of the short hash. But hash algorithms are fast, and it
is possible to try millions of values in less than a second. If the short
string is made up of fewer than 6 digits, Eve will find a matching nonce 
quickly, and Alice and Bob will hardly notice the delay. Even if the 
matching string is as long as 8 letters, Eve will probably find a value
where the short versions of h' and h" are close enough, e.g. start and end
with the same two or three letters. Alice and Bob may well be fooled.
</t>
<t>
The classic solution to such problems is to "commit" a possible attacker to a nonce before sending it.
This commitment can be realized by a hash.
In the modified exchange, Alice sends a secure
hash of her nonce before sending the actual value:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
    Alice                       Bob
    g^xA --&gt;
                            &lt;-- g^xB

    Computes              Computes
    s = g^xAxB            s = g^xAxB
    h_a = hash(s|nA) --&gt;
                              &lt;-- nB
    nA --&gt;
                          verifies h_a == hash(s|nA)
    Computes              Computes
    h = hash(s|nA|nB)     h = hash(s|nA|nB)
    Displays short        Displays short
    version of h          version of h
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
Alice will only disclose nA after
having confirmation from Bob that hash(nA) has been received.
At that point, Eve has a problem. She can still forge the values of the nonces
but she needs to pick the nonce nA' before the actual value of nA has been 
disclosed.
Eve would still have a random chance of fooling Alice and Bob, but it will be a very
small chance: one in a million if the short authentication string is made of
6 digits, even fewer if that string is longer. 
</t>
<t>
Nguyen et al. <xref target="NR11" /> survey these protocols and compare them with respect to the amount of necessary user interaction and
  the computation time needed on the devices.
  The authors state that such a protocol is optimal with respect to user interaction if it suffices for users to verify a single b-bit SAS
  while having a one-shot attack success probability of 2^-b.
  Further, n consecutive attacks on the protocol must not have a better success probability then n one-shot attacks.
</t>
<t>
There is still a theoretical problem, if Eve has somehow managed to 
"crack" the hash function. We build some "defense in depth" by 
some simple measures. In the design presented above, the hash "h_a"
depends on the shared secret "s", which acts as a "salt" and reduces
the effectiveness of potential attacks based on pre-computed 
catalogs. For simplicity, the design used a simple concatenation 
mechanism, but we could instead use a keyed-hash message authentication 
code (HMAC, <xref target="RFC2104"/>, <xref target="RFC6151"/>), using 
the shared secret as a key, since the HMAC construct has
proven very robust over time. Then, we can constrain the size of
the random numbers to be exactly the same as the output of the hash 
function. Hash attacks often require padding the input string with
arbitrary data; restraining the size limits the likelyhood of such 
padding.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Privacy Requirements" >
<t>
Pairing exposes a relation between several devices and their owners. Adversaries may
attempt to collect this information, for example in an attempt to track 
devices, their owners, or their "social graph." It is often argued that
pairing could be performed in a safe place, from which adversaries are assumed 
absent, but experience shows that such assumptions are often misguided.
It is much safer to acknowledge the privacy issues and design the pairing
process accordingly.
</t>
<t>
In order to start the pairing process, devices must first discover each other.
We do not have the option of
using the private discovery protocol <xref target="I-D.huitema-dnssd-privacy" /> 
since the privacy of that protocol depends on the pre-existing pairing. 
In the simplest design, 
one of the devices will announce a "friendly name" using DNS-SD. 
Adversaries could monitor the discovery protocol, and record that name.
An alternative would be for one device to announce a random name, and communicate
it to the other device via some private channel. There is an obvious
tradeoff here: friendly names are easier to use but less private than
random names. We anticipate that different users will choose different
tradeoffs, for example using friendly names if they assume that
the environment is "safe," and using random names in public places.
</t>
<t>
During the pairing process, the two devices establish a connection
and validate a pairing secret. As discussed in <xref target="MITMUIReq" />,
we have to assume that adversaries can mount MITM attacks. The pairing 
protocol can detect such attacks and resist them, but the attackers will
have access to all messages exchanged before validation
is performed. It is important to not exchange any privacy sensitive information
before that validation. This includes, for example, the identities of the
parties or their public keys.
</t>

</section>

<section title="Using TLS" >
<t>
The pairing algorithms typically combine the establishment of a shared
secret through an [EC]DH exchange with the verification of that secret
through displaying and comparison of a "short authentication string" (SAS).
As explained in <xref target="MITMCryptoReq" />, the
secure comparison requires a "commit before disclose" mechanism.
</t>
<t>
We have three possible designs: (1) create a pairing algorithm from scratch,
specifying our own crypto exchanges; (2) use an [EC]DH version of TLS to
negotiate a shared secret, export the key to the application as specified 
in <xref target="RFC5705" />, and implement
the "commit before disclose" and SAS verification as part of the pairing
application; or, (3) use TLS, integrate the "commit before disclose" and SAS
verification as TLS extensions, and export the verified key to the
application as specified 
in <xref target="RFC5705" />.
</t>
<t>
When faced with the same choice, the designers of ZRTP <xref target="RFC6189" />
chose to design a new protocol integrated in the general framework of real
time communications. We don't want to follow that path, and would rather not
create yet another protocol. We would need to
reinvent a lot of the negotiation capabilities that are part of TLS, not
to mention algorithm agility, post quantum, and all that sort of things. 
It is thus pretty clear that we should use TLS.
</t>
<t>
It turns out that there was already an attempt to define 
SAS extensions for TLS (<xref target="I-D.miers-tls-sas" />). 
It is a very close match
to our third design option, full integration of SAS in TLS,
but the draft has expired, and there does not seem to be
any support for the SAS options in the common TLS packages.
</t>
<t>
In our design, we will choose the middle ground option -- use TLS for
[EC]DH,
and implement the SAS verification as part of the pairing application.
This minimizes dependencies on TLS packages to the availability
of a key export API following <xref target="RFC5705" />.
We will need to specify the hash algorithm used for the SAS
computation and validation, which carries some of the issues
associated with "designing our own crypto". One
solution would be to use the same hash algorithm negotiated by
the TLS connection, but common TLS packages do not not always 
make this algorithm identifier available
through standard APIs. A fallback solution is to
specify a state of the art keyed MAC algorithm.
</t>
</section>

<section title="QR codes" anchor="QRDiscuss" >
<t>
In <xref target="shortRange" />, we reviewed a number of short range 
communication systems that can be used to facilitate pairing. Out of these,
QR codes stand aside because most devices that can display a short
string can also display the image of a QR code, and because many
pairing scenarios involve cell phones equipped with cameras capable of
reading a QR code.
</t>
<t>
QR codes could be particularly useful when starting discovery. QR codes can
encode an alphanumeric string, which could for example encode the
selected name of the pairing service.
This would enable automatic discovery, and would be easier to use than reading
the random name of the day and matching it against the results of DNS-SD.
</t>
<t>
In addition to the instance name, a QR code could also be leveraged for authentication.
It could encode an SAS or even a longer authentication string. Transmitting the output of a
cryptographic hash function or HMAC via the OOB channel would make an offline combinatorial search attack infeasible
and thus allow to not sent the commitment discussed in <xref target="MITMCryptoReq" /> saving a message.
Further, if a single device created both QR codes for discovery and verifcation, respecitvely,
and the other device scans these, the users could just wait while both QRs are scanned subsequently as
no user interaction is necessary between these two scans (but it needs a QR scanner (app) that support this). 
This could make the process feel like a single user interaction.
</t>
<t>
But still, from a users point of view, scanning QR codes
may not be more efficient than visual verification of a short string.
The user has to take a picture of the QR code, which is arguably not 
simpler than just "look at the number on the screen and tell me whether it is 
the same as yours".
</t>
<t>
In the case of a man-in-the-middle attack, the evaluation of the QR code will fail. 
The "client" that took the picture will know that, but the "server" will not. The 
user will still need to click some "Cancel" button on the server, which means that
the process will not be completely automated.
</t>

</section>

</section> <!-- end of problem statement -->

<section title="Design of the Pairing Mechanism" anchor="design" >

<t>
In this section we discuss the design of pairing protocols that use manually 
verified short authentication strings (SAS), considering both security and user experience.
</t>

<t>
 We divide pairing in three parts: discovery, agreement, and authentication, detailed in the following subsections.
</t>

<section title="Discovery">
<t>
The goal of the discovery phase is establishing a connection, which is later used to
exchange the pairing data, between the two devices that are about to be paired
in an IP network without any a priori knowledge and without publishing any private information.
In accordance with TLS, we refer to the device initiating the cryptographic protocol as client,
and to the other device as server; the server has to be discoverable by the client.
</t>
<t>
Granting privacy during the discovery phase without relying on a priori knowledge demands another user interaction (besides
the SAS verification during the authentication phase).
There are two possible ways of realizing this user interaction depending on whether QR codes are supported or not.
If QR codes are supported, the discovery process can be independent of DNS-SD, because 
QR codes allow the transmission of a sufficient amount of data.
Leveraging QR codes, the discovery proceeds as follows.
</t>
<t>
<list style="numbers">
<t>
  The server displays a QR code containing the clients A and AAAA resource records,
  and further the SRV resource record corresponding to the pairing service instance. A privacy preserving instance name is not
  necessary, because this instance is never published via an unsecured network.
</t>
<t>
The client scans the QR code retrieving the necessary information for establishing a connection to the server.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
If QR codes are not supported, the discovery proceeds as follows.
</t>
<t>
<list style="numbers">
<t>
The server displays its chosen instance name on its screen.  
</t>
<t>
The client performs a discovery of all the "pairing" servers
available on the local network. This may result in the discovery
of several servers.
</t>
<t>
Among these available "pairing servers" the client user 
selects the name that matches the name displayed by the server.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Agreement">
<t>
Once the server has been selected, the client connects to it without further user intervention.
Client and server use this connection for exchanging data that allows them to agree on a shared secret
by using a cryptographic protocol that yields an SAS. We discussed design aspects of such protocols in <xref target="MITMCryptoReq" />.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Authentication">
<t>
In the authentication phase, the users are asked to validate the pairing by comparing the SASes -- typically represented by a number encoded over up to 7 decimal digits.
If the SASes match, each user enters an agreement, for example by pressing a button labeled "OK", which results in the pairing being remembered.
If they do not match, each user should cancel the pairing, for example by pressing a button labeled "CANCEL". 
</t>

<t>
Depending on whether QR codes are supported, the SAS may also be represented as QR code.
Despite the fact that using QR codes to represent the authentication string renders using longer authentication strings feasible,
we suggest to always generate an SAS during the agreement phase, because this makes realizations of the agreement phase and the authentication phase independent.
Devices may display the "real" name of the other device alongside the SAS.
</t>

</section>


<section title="Intra User Pairing">
  <t>
  Users can pair their own devices in secure (home) networks without any interaction using a special DNS-SD pairing service.
  Verification methods where a  single user holds both devices, e.g. synchronously pressing buttons on both devices a few times, are also suitable.
  Further, a secure OOB could be established by connecting two devices with an USB channel.
  Pairing via an USB connection is also used by some Bluetooth devices, e.g. when pairing a controller with a gaming console.
  </t>
  <t>
    [[TODO: elaborate]]
  </t>

</section>

<section title="Pairing Data Synchronization">
  <t>
    To make it sufficient for users to pair only one of their devices to one of their friends devices while still
    being able to engage in later communication with all of this friend's devices using any of the own devices,
    we offer the possibility to synchronize pairing data among devices of the same user.
    Pairing data synchronization is performed via a special DNS-SD service (_pdsync._tls).
  </t>
  <t>
    [[TODO: elaborate]]
  </t>
</section>




<section title="Public Authentication Keys">
  <t>
    [[TODO: Should we discuss public authentication keys whose fingerprints are verified during pairing?]]
</t>
</section>

</section>


<section title="Solution" anchor="solution" >

  <t>
    [[TODO: elaborate on all subsections]]
  </t>

<t>
In the proposed pairing protocol, one of the devices acts as a "server", and the other acts as a "client". 
The server will publish a "pairing service". The client will discover the service instance during the
discovery phase, as explained in <xref target="discoverSpec"/>. The pairing service itself is specified 
in <xref target="serviceSpec" />.

</t>

<section title="Discovery" anchor="discoverSpec" >
<t>
The discovery uses DNS-SD <xref target="RFC6763" /> over mDNS <xref target="RFC6762" />.
The pairing service is identified in DNS SD as "_pairing._tcp".
When the pairing service starts, the server starts publishing the chosen instance name.
The client will discover that name and the corresponding connection parameters.
</t>
<t>
If QR code scanning is available as OOB channel, the discovery data is
directly transmitted via QR codes instead of DNS-SD over mDNS.
[[TODO: We should precisely specify the data layout of this QR code.
It could either be the wire format of the corresponding resource records (which would be easier for us),
or a more efficient representation. If we chose the wire format, we could use a fix name as instance name.]]
</t>
</section>

<section title="Agreement and Authentication" anchor="serviceSpec">
<t>
The pairing protocol is built using TLS. The following description uses the
presentation language defined in section 4 of <xref target="RFC5246" />.
The protocol uses five message types, defined in the following enum:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
enum {
   ClientHash(1),
   ServerRandom(2),
   ClientRandom(3),
   ServerSuccess(4),
   ClientSuccess(5)
} PairingMessageType;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
Devices implementing the service MUST 
support TLS 1.2 <xref target="RFC5246" />, and SHOULD support TLS 1.3 as soon as 
it becomes available.
When using TLS, the client and server MUST negotiate a ciphersuite
providing forward secrecy (PFS), and strong encryption (256 bits symmetric 
key). All implementations using TLS 1.2 SHOULD be able to negotiate
the cipher suite TLS_DH_anon_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA256.
</t>
<t>
Once the TLS connection has been established, each party extracts the pairing secret 
S_p from the connection context per <xref target="RFC5705" />, using the following 
parameters:
</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
<t hangText="Disambiguating label string:" >
"PAIRING SECRET"
</t>
<t hangText="Context value:" >
empty.
</t>
<t hangText="Length value:">
32 bytes (256 bits).
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Once S_p has been obtained, the client picks a random number R_c, exactly 32 bytes 
long. The client then selects a hash algorithm, which SHOULD be the same algorithm as 
negotiated for building the PRF in the TLS connection. If there is no suitable API to 
retrieve that algorithm, the client MAY use SHA256 instead. The client then computes 
the hash value H_c as:
</t>
<t>
<list>
<t>
H_c = HMAC_hash(S_p, R_c)
</t>
<t>
Where "HMAC_hash" is the HMAC function constructed with the selected algorithm.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
The client transmits the selected hash function and the computed value of H_c 
in the Client Hash message, over the TLS connection:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
struct {
   PairingMessageType messageType;
   hashAlgorithm hash;
   uint8 hashLength;
   opaque H_c[hashLength];
} ClientHashMessage;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
<t hangText="messageType" >
Set to "ClientHash".
</t>
<t hangText="hash" >
The code of the selected hash algorithm, per definition of HashAlgorithm in section 7.4.1.1.1 of <xref target="RFC5246" />.
</t>
<t hangText="hashLength" >
The length of the hash H_c, which MUST be consistent with the selected algorithm "hash".
</t>
<t hangText="H_c" >
The value of the client hash.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Upon reception of this message, the server stores its value. The server picks a random number R_s,
exactly 32 bytes long, and transmits it to the client in the server random message, over the TLS connection:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
struct {
   PairingMessageType messageType;
   opaque R_s[32];
} ServerRandomMessage;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
<t hangText="messageType" >
Set to "ServerRandom".
</t>
<t hangText="R_s" >
The value of the random number chosen by the server.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Upon reception of this message, the client discloses its own random
number by transmitting the client random message:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
struct {
   PairingMessageType messageType;
   opaque R_c[32];
} ClientRandomMessage;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
<t hangText="messageType" >
Set to "ClientRandom".
</t>
<t hangText="R_c" >
The value of the random number chosen by the client.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Upon reception of this message, the server verifies that the 
number R_c hashes to the previously received value H_c. If
the number does not match, the server MUST abandon the pairing
attempt and abort the TLS connection.
</t>
<t>
At this stage, both client and server can compute the short
hash SAS as:
</t>
<t>
<list>
<t>
SAS = first 20 bits of HMAC_hash(S_p, R_c + R_s)
</t>
<t>
Where "HMAC_hash" is the HMAC function constructed with the hash
algorithm selected by the client in the ClientHashMessage.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Both client and server display the SAS as a decimal integer,
and ask the user to compare the values. If the values do not match, the user
cancels the pairing. Otherwise, the protocol continues with the
exchange of names, both server and client announcing their own preferred
name in a Success message
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
struct {
   PairingMessageType messageType;
   uint8 nameLength;
   opaque name[nameLength];
} ClientSuccessMessage;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
<list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
<t hangText="messageType" >
Set to "ClientSuccess" if transmitted by the client, "ServerSuccess" if by the server.
</t>
<t hangText="nameLength" >
The length of the string encoding the selected name.
</t>
<t hangText="name" >
The selected name of the client or the server, encoded as a string of UTF8 characters.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
After receiving these messages, client and servers can orderly close the TLS connection, 
terminating the pairing exchange.
</t>
</section>



</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">
<t>
We need to consider two types of attacks against a pairing 
system: attacks that occur during the establishment of the 
pairing relation, and attacks that occur after that 
establishment.
</t>

<t>
During the establishment of the pairing system, we are
concerned with privacy attacks and with MITM attacks. Privacy attacks
reveal the existence of a pairing between two devices, which can be used 
to track graphs of relations. MITM attacks result in compromised pairing
keys. The
discovery procedures specified in <xref target="discoverSpec" /> 
and the authentication procedures specified in 
<xref target="serviceSpec" /> are specifically designed to
mitigate such attacks.
</t>

<t>
The establishment of the pairing results in the creation of a shared
secret. After the establishment of the pairing relation, 
attackers who compromise one of the device could access the shared
secret. This will enable them to either track or spoof the devices. 
To mitigate such attacks, nodes MUST store the secret safely,
and MUST be able to quickly revoke
a compromised pairing. This is however not sufficient, as the
compromise of the pairing key could remain undetected for
a long time. For further safety, nodes SHOULD assign a time limit
to the validity of pairings, discard the corresponding keys when
the time has passed, and establish new pairings.
</t>

</section>


<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
<t>
This draft does not require any IANA action.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgments">
    <t>
      TODO
    </t>
</section>
</middle>

<back>
<references title="Normative References">
       &rfc2119;
       &rfc5246;
       &rfc5705;
       &rfc6763;
       &rfc6762;
</references>
<references title="Informative References">
       &rfc2104;
       &rfc6151;
       &rfc6189;
       &I-D.huitema-dnssd-privacy;
       &I-D.miers-tls-sas;

<reference anchor="NR11" target="">
  <front>
    <title>Authentication protocols based on low-bandwidth unspoofable channels: a comparative survey</title>
    <author initials="L." surname="Nguyen" fullname="Long Hoang Nguyen">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Roscoe" fullname="Andrew William Roscoe">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <date year="2011"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="KFR09" target="">
  <front>
    <title>Authentication protocols based on low-bandwidth unspoofable channels: a comparative survey</title>
    <author initials="R." surname="Kainda" fullname="Ronald Kainda">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <author initials="I." surname="Flechais" fullname="Ivan Flechais">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Roscoe" fullname="Andrew William Roscoe">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <date year="2009"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="USK11" target="">
  <front>
    <title>. Pairing devices for social interactions: a comparative usability evaluation </title>
    <author initials="E." surname="Uzun" fullname="Ersin Uzun">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <author initials="N." surname="Saxena" fullname="Nitesh Saxena">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Kumar" fullname="Arun Kumar">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <date year="2009"/>
  </front>
</reference>


<reference anchor="XKCD936" target="https://www.xkcd.com/936/" >
   <front>
    <title>XKCD: Password Strength</title>
    <author initials="R." surname="Munroe" fullname="Randall Munroe">
      <organization/>
    </author>
    <date year="2011"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="BTLEPairing" target="https://developer.bluetooth.org/TechnologyOverview/Pages/LE-Security.aspx">
  <front>
    <title>Bluetooth Low Energy Security Overview</title>
    <author>
      <organization>Bluetooth SIG</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2016"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="WPS" target="http://www.wi-fi.org/discover-wi-fi/wi-fi-protected-setup">
  <front>
    <title>Wi-Fi Protected Setup</title>
    <author>
      <organization>Wi-Fi Alliance</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2016"/>
  </front>
</reference>
</references>

</back>
</rfc>
